<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>GetShredGo</title>
    <link href="https://getshredgo.net/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://getshredgo.net" />
    <updated>2022-10-28T15:44:45+05:30</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Rish</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://getshredgo.net</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Indian Diet Plan for Breastfeeding Mothers</title>
        <author>
            <name>Rish</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://getshredgo.net/indian-diet-plan-for-breastfeeding-mothers/"/>
        <id>https://getshredgo.net/indian-diet-plan-for-breastfeeding-mothers/</id>
        <media:content url="https://getshredgo.net/media/posts/25/hollie-santos-aUtvHsu8Uzk-unsplash.jpg" medium="image" />

        <updated>2022-10-20T20:16:54+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://getshredgo.net/media/posts/25/hollie-santos-aUtvHsu8Uzk-unsplash.jpg" alt="" />
                    Nutritional status of the mother has a direct influence on the quality and quantity of her breastmilk. A breastfeeding mother&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://getshredgo.net/media/posts/25/hollie-santos-aUtvHsu8Uzk-unsplash.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p>Nutritional status of the mother has a direct influence on the quality and quantity of her breastmilk. A breastfeeding mother needs to consume an adequate and balanced diet. There is an extra demand for nutrients, especially to secrete adequate quantity/quality of milk and to safeguard your own health.</p>
<p><img src="https://i.postimg.cc/Pf975Sts/andriyko-podilnyk-yhk-zsfgw0g-unsplash-1.jpg"></p>
<h2><strong>Important Tips for an Indian diet plan for lactating mothers:</strong></h2>
<p>It is true that a lactating mother needs to eat for two people as long as she’s going to be feeding the baby. The mother must get sufficient nutrition else the baby will derive nutrients from the mother’s body and she may suffer from nutritional deficiencies and many other problems.</p>
<ul>
<li>Lactating mothers feel hungry more often and they should eat whenever they feel so.</li>
<li>When a baby doesn’t get nutritious milk, She will become unhealthy and also demand frequent feeds.</li>
<li>The stress should be on getting extra nutrition and not extra calories. This is important both for the mother and the baby.</li>
<li>Extra calories are only going to add on the weight and will not help with the growth of the baby nor will they give strength to the mother. Our Indian diet plan for lactating mothers will give you an insight into the right food choices you need to make.</li>
</ul>
<div class="content-box-gray">
<h2>The fear of becoming Obese in Lactating Mothers:</h2>
<p>Many mothers fear that they will become fat and look clumsy. You must remember that your child is your first responsibility and his growth depends on you. Secondly, research has shown that mothers who breastfeed their babies are able to shed weight more easily than those who don’t. Let us now see the detailed Indian diet plan for lactating mothers.</p>
</div>
<h2><strong>Energy</strong></h2>
<p>It takes extra energy to produce breast milk. Mothers need an additional 400 calories on an average per day beyond their normal health requirement.</p>
<h2><strong>Protein</strong></h2>
<p>The Recommended Dietary Allowance for protein during lactation includes an additional 15 grams per day (RDA of 65 grams per day) in the first six months after childbirth and an additional 12 grams per day (RDA of 62 grams per day) thereafter.</p>
<h2><strong>Fluids</strong></h2>
<p>Adequate fluids to stay hydrated include 2 to 3 liters per day, or at least eight 8-ounce servings, and can include water, milk or soy milk, decaffeinated beverages etc. Limit caffeine to the equivalent of one cup of coffee a day to avoid causing the baby agitation or difficulty in sleeping.</p>
<h2><strong>Vitamins and Minerals</strong></h2>
<p>Food supplies the vitamins and minerals lactating mothers especially need, such as calcium, vitamin A, vitamin C, vitamin D and zinc. Vitamin and mineral supplements do not replace a healthful diet, but some breastfeeding women might need a multivitamin and mineral supplement in addition to eating a well-balanced diet.</p>
<p><img src="https://i.postimg.cc/02SBM7Q6/Bmilk.webp"></p>
<h2><strong>Special consideration in lactating mother’s diet</strong></h2>
<p>Eating well while breastfeeding entails getting the right balance of good (and good for you) food. Try to get the following each day:</p>
<p>1. Protein: Three servings<br>2. Calcium: Five servings (that’s an increase from your pregnancy requirement of four)<br>3. Iron-rich foods: One or more servings<br>4. Vitamin C: Two servings<br>5. Green leafy and yellow vegetables, yellow fruits: Three to four servings<br>6. Other fruits and veggies: One or more servings<br>7. Whole-grain and other concentrated complex carbohydrates: Three or more servings<br>8. High-fat foods: small amounts – you don’t need as much as you did during pregnancy<br>9. Eight cups of water, juice, or other non caffeinated, non-alcoholic beverages<br>10. DHA-rich foods to promote baby’s brain growth (look for it in wild salmon and sardines, as well as DHA-enriched eggs).</p>
<p>Lactation is a very important and beautiful phase in both the mother’s and the child’s life. This is a phase when the bonding between mother and the child is built and strengthened. Mother’s milk is vital for the child’s growth and the importance of the right nutrition at this point is unquestionable.</p>
<table style="border-collapse: collapse; width: 100%;" border="1">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="width: 49.9288%;"><strong>Morning:<br>8:00 am </strong></td>
<td style="width: 49.9288%;">1 cup tea (1 tsp sugar) + 7-8 soaked almonds and 4-5 dates</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="width: 49.9288%;"><strong>Breakfast:<br>9:00 am</strong></td>
<td style="width: 49.9288%;">
<p>1 glass (200 ml) skimmed milk + 1/2 cup badam sheera + 1 Fruit OR 3 small methi or palak paratha + ½ cup curd/raita OR 3 slices of whole wheat bread and 2 eggs + 1 fruit or 1 cup of poha OR upma + 1 fruit + 1 sunth vadi</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="width: 49.9288%;"><strong>Mid Morning:<br>11:00 am</strong></td>
<td style="width: 49.9288%;">
<p>1 fruit + 1 methi ladoo</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="width: 49.9288%;"><strong>Lunch::<br>1:00 pm</strong></td>
<td style="width: 49.9288%;">
<div class="col-md-9">
<p class="mealTime">1 cup salad + 2 rotis or 2 small bajra rotis 1 cup rice + 1 cup vegetables + 1 cup moong curry/dal OR 1 cup salad + 2 rotis + 1 cup rice + 1 cup vegetables + 1 cup fish curry</p>
</div>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="width: 49.9288%;"><strong>Evening:<br>4:00 pm</strong></td>
<td style="width: 49.9288%;">
<div class="col-md-9">
<p class="mealTime">1 glass milk (200ml) + 1 goand ladoo</p>
</div>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="width: 49.9288%;"><strong>Mid Eve:<br>6:00 pm</strong></td>
<td style="width: 49.9288%;">
<div class="col-md-9">
<p class="mealTime">1 cup tea (1tsp sugar) with<br>2 small pan cakes (Puda/chila) or Sprout bhel or<br>1 cup vegetable upma</p>
</div>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="width: 49.9288%;"><strong>Dinner:<br>9:00 pm</strong></td>
<td style="width: 49.9288%;">
<div class="col-md-9">
<p class="mealTime">1 cup salad + 2 rotis+ 1 cup rice +<br>1 cup leafy vegetable + 1 cup dal</p>
</div>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="width: 49.9288%;"><strong>Bed Time</strong></td>
<td style="width: 49.9288%;">
<div class="col-md-9">
<p class="mealTime">1 glass milk (200ml)</p>
</div>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table style="border-collapse: collapse; width: 100%;" border="1">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="width: 99.8575%;">*Fruits: any seasonal fruits such as apple pear, grapes, melons, banana etc.<br>**Salads: carrot, cucumber, tomato, cabbage, beetroot, lettuce, etc.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p class="msg msg--highlight "><strong>DISCLAIMER: The above is suggestive meal plan, please consult with your dietician before following this plan</strong></p>
<h2><img src="https://i.postimg.cc/qvdZ8gh1/jonathan-borba-8-C-Iaq-Aujw-M-unsplash-1.jpg"></h2>
<h2>Breastfeeding Mother's Diet Plan FAQs</h2>
<h2 id="section2" class="">Do I need more calories when I am breastfeeding?</h2>
<p>You don't need to have extra calories as a new mum, because your body is so efficient at making milk. <br><br>Be guided by your appetite, and eat when you're hungry. It's normal for your body to lay down fat stores during pregnancy to help you prepare for breastfeeding. Breastfeeding your baby can help to convert these fat stores into energy for making milk.<br><br>You may have come across different advice about extra calories when you're breastfeeding. But it's hard to say whether you need extra calories every day, because so much depends on:</p>
<ul>
<li>your pre-pregnancy weight</li>
<li>how much weight you gained during pregnancy</li>
<li>how active you are</li>
</ul>
<p><br>Having said that, breastfeeding usually gives you a big appetite. So if you don't feel like eating, it could be a sign that you need extra emotional support. <br><br>Women who have postnatal depression sometimes lose their appetite. If you're finding it a struggle to eat, talk to your doctor.</p>
<h2 id="section3" class="">Do I need to drink more water and fluids to maintain my breastmilk supply?</h2>
<p>You only need to drink enough to satisfy your thirst while you're breastfeeding. <br><br>You may have been told that you should drink lots of water to keep up your milk supply, but in reality drinking lots of water, or indeed going a bit thirsty, won't affect the amount of milk you make. Your body is good at regulating its reserves to make sure it keeps your milk supply going.</p>
<p>Breastfeeding can make you thirsty so it’s always a good idea to keep a glass of water, coconut water, or fresh juice close by when you nurse your baby. You also need to be cautious about drinking clean boiled or filtered water to avoid water borne infections. It is best to carry a bottle of water with you when you go out or opt for a well-known brand of mineral water. <br><br>If you are used to having aerated drinks to quench your thirst it is best to avoid these while breastfeeding. They contain just empty calories and no nutrition. You could instead substitute it with healthier drinks such as <i>lassi</i>, coconut water, buttermilk (<i>chhaach</i>), fresh fruit and vegetable juices or <i>nimbu pani</i>.<br><br>If you’re worried about whether you’re getting enough to drink, check the colour of your urine. If it’s pale-coloured, you’re getting plenty to drink. If it’s dark yellow, or smells strongly, or if you feel lethargic or faint, you may be dehydrated, in which case you should drink more water.</p>
<h2 id="section4" class="">Can I drink tea and coffee if I'm breastfeeding?</h2>
<p>Try not to have too many caffeinated drinks when you're breastfeeding. This can be tough, especially in the early days when you're exhausted from breastfeeding round the clock. <br><br>It is recommended you keep your caffeine intake below 200mg a day. It's hard to estimate how much caffeine is in a cappuccino or latte, so you may be safer to stick with decaffeinated coffee or herbal tea when you're out and about. Keep in mind that there is caffeine in cola, energy drinks and chocolate as well. <br><br>If your baby seems very unsettled or restless, or finds it difficult to sleep, try cutting back on caffeine, or not having any at all. This may help your baby to settle more easily.</p>
<h2 id="section5" class="">Can I drink alcohol if I'm breastfeeding?</h2>
<p>Alcohol passes through your breastmilk to your baby. It could harm your baby if you drink more than two units of alcohol more than once or twice a week. <br><br>It's always best to be cautious, so you may want to cut out alcohol while you're breastfeeding, especially in the first three months. <br><br>When he's a newborn, your baby's stomach is very small and will need filling up often. The amount of alcohol in your blood peaks between 30 minutes and 90 minutes after you have a drink. If your baby is feeding often, there won't be enough time between feeds for the alcohol to clear from your system.<br><br>Your baby's liver is immature too, and needs protecting from traces of alcohol. <br><br></p>
<h2 id="section6" class="">Can I have herbal remedies?</h2>
<p>You can drink most herbal teas when you are breastfeeding as long as you don't drink them in large amounts. <br><br>Herbal teas which use ingredients you might cook with, such as, fenugreek (<i>methi</i>), cumin (<i>jeera</i>), green cardamom (<i>chhoti elaichi</i>), fennel (<i>saunf</i>), garlic (<i>lehsun</i>), camomile and peppermint, are thought to be safe to drink.<br><br>You may also be offered traditional drinks prepared with specific herbs. It's best to check with your doctor before including any herbs in your diet.</p>
<h2 id="section7" class="">Do I need to take any supplements when I'm breastfeeding?</h2>
<p>Most lactating mothers are advised to take daily supplements of iron, folic acid, vitamin B and calcium. After evaluating your diet your doctor will advise you on which supplements you need.<br><br>If a blood test shows you have a vitamin D deficiency, your doctor will prescribe supplements. Don’t take any supplements, even herbal and natural ones, without consulting with your doctor first. <br><br>If you do take supplements, bear in mind that it can’t make up for poor eating habits. It is also important to eat a well-balanced, varied diet.</p>
<h2 id="section8" class="">Can I lose weight while I'm breastfeeding?</h2>
<p>You should be fine to lose weight gradually. Losing about 500g to 1kg a week shouldn't affect the amount or the quality of milk you make. <br><br>It may be best to wait until you've had your postnatal check at about six weeks to eight weeks before you actively try to diet. <br><br>Then you can discuss the best ways to eat healthily and exercise with your doctor. <br><br>Bear in mind that you'll need to keep up your strength as a new mum. Trying to do too much after giving birth may slow your recovery and make you feel even more tired. This is especially the case if you've had a caesarean, or a difficult birth.</p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><strong>Ready to start your journey? </strong></p>
<p class="align-center"><a href="https://form.jotform.com/221365212070442" class="btn hero__btn" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Enroll Now</a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>How to lose weight during pregnancy</title>
        <author>
            <name>Rish</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://getshredgo.net/how-to-lose-weight-during-pregnancy/"/>
        <id>https://getshredgo.net/how-to-lose-weight-during-pregnancy/</id>
        <media:content url="https://getshredgo.net/media/posts/21/jonathan-borba-GpfRAzKjngw-unsplash.jpg" medium="image" />

        <updated>2022-10-20T20:17:52+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://getshredgo.net/media/posts/21/jonathan-borba-GpfRAzKjngw-unsplash.jpg" alt="" />
                    ‍ Your body starts to grow during your third trimester. Your belly grows along with it, as does your voice&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://getshredgo.net/media/posts/21/jonathan-borba-GpfRAzKjngw-unsplash.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <figure class="post__image post__image--center"><img  src="https://img.freepik.com/premium-vector/exercise-set-pregnant-woman-sport-during-pregnancy-idea-active-healthy-lifestyle-illustration-cartoon-style_277904-4356.jpg" alt="By Best Online Personal Trainer Nutritionist Dietician India" width="600"></figure>‍</p>
<p>Your body starts to grow during your third trimester. Your belly grows along with it, as does your voice and your hair. But these changes don’t mean that you can’t still gain weight. In fact, you might actually start to lose it during the pregnancy. During this time of growth and development, your fat begins to melt away.</p>
<p>This means that instead of packing on weight as you do during her second trimester, your belly will curve in a more natural way. And it will also mean that from here on out, you won’t be gaining any more skin or muscle-tone-changing pounds throughout the entire third trimester! </p>
<h2><strong>What is the difference between gaining weight and losing it during pregnancy?</strong></h2>
<p>As we mentioned above, your fat Developes during your third and fourth months of pregnancy. And this is also the time when your body is most likely going to start to produce the hormones that are necessary for fat loss. But during this time, your body is also going to be absorbing some of the nutrients with which it is already in contact. And one of these nutrients is vitamin B2, B3 and B5 (antioxidants). A few pages back, we mentioned that pregnant women can increase their intake of fruits and vegetables during this period to help improve the level of these vitamins in the body. Fruits and vegetables not only provide a good source of antioxidants, they also contain antioxidants that are needed for your unborn baby to develop properly. Furthermore, consuming a healthy amount of fibre (fiber is required for proper digestion) will help your baby’s body to absorb the minerals that are needed for him/her to grow.</p>
<h2><strong>Belly fat during pregnancy: What’s good about it?</strong></h2>
<p>Belly fat is a normal and healthy part of pregnancy. You will probably see it around your lower region after the second or third month of pregnancy. This is because your baby’s stomach is growing and twisting around as he/she is fed by the mom’s body. It is however important to not allow this fatty tissue to build up too much. This can lead to heart disease, metabolic derangement and even low-birth-weight baby. The best way to control this fat is to consume a healthy amount of carbohydrates throughout the day. This will help to break down your existing fatty tissue into more manageable pieces.</p>
<h2><strong>Belly fat during pregnancy: Bad for weight loss</strong></h2>
<p>Well, everyone has a favorite diet, and there is no contest in this regard. The only real way to lose weight during pregnancy is to follow a healthy eating plan. A healthy diet should consist of fruits, vegetables, whole grains, lean meats and vegetables, light fats, and drinks that will keep your blood pressure moderate (spirits, coffee, etc.). Carbohydrates should comprise of sweets, pastries, and meringue. Fruits should be eaten in moderate amounts throughout the day. And the last thing you should be doing during this non-working period is lifting heavy weights. Doing so will only cause your stomach to expand and cause more fat to build up.</p>
<h2><strong>How to lose weight during pregnancy: Start with a healthy diet and keep on top of your exercise routine</strong></h2>
<p>A daily healthy diet can help you to control your hunger pangs. Since you are generally less likely to consume foods that will give you energy, you will be less likely to consume large amounts of calories in the form of fat. A healthy diet should consist of fruits, vegetables, whole grains, legumes, and proteins. A healthy snack should consist of minimally-calorie items. If you must consume large amounts of calories, these should be broken down into less- calorie-containing components. Exercising can help you to stay toned and flexible. It is therefore a good idea to keep your exercise routine on a keep-away from too heavy a frame. Some easy exercises that you can do at home that are easy on your body include: Bicycle ergometry (BEE) – This is a aerobic exercise that can help you to stay toned. It is therefore good for all stages of pregnancy. Cardiotomy – This is a prone- position exercise that can help to reduce your risk of Ulcers and cerebral palsy. It is therefore a good idea to maintain your upright position throughout pregnancy. Cross-exchangeability – This is a type of passive land management that will help your body to stay happy and healthy throughout the pregnancy.</p>
<h2><strong>Bottom line</strong></h2>
<p>Your diet can help you to control your hunger pangs, a daily healthy diet can help you to control your weight gain, and exercise is a key to weight loss. Keep in mind that food isn’t everything when it comes to losing weight during pregnancy. A healthy diet is a crucial part of nutrition during pregnancy. Your doctor will discuss the right foods to put in your diet and how to balance them with your exercise routine during pregnancy.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>How to lose weight while working from home</title>
        <author>
            <name>Rish</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://getshredgo.net/how-to-lose-weight-while-working-from-home/"/>
        <id>https://getshredgo.net/how-to-lose-weight-while-working-from-home/</id>
        <media:content url="https://getshredgo.net/media/posts/19/magnet-me-LDcC7aCWVlo-unsplash-1.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="Diet &amp; Exercise"/>

        <updated>2022-10-01T21:33:24+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://getshredgo.net/media/posts/19/magnet-me-LDcC7aCWVlo-unsplash-1.jpg" alt="" />
                    Weight loss is a common issue faced by people. Many people want to lose weight but are afraid of going&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://getshredgo.net/media/posts/19/magnet-me-LDcC7aCWVlo-unsplash-1.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p>Weight loss is a common issue faced by people. Many people want to lose weight but are afraid of going to the gym. They don't want to gain any extra stress while trying to slim down. However, there are plenty of ways to slim down without going to the gym. Using exercises at home is a great way to lose weight. It's also a lot more effective than dieting alone.</p>
<p><br>One of the best ways to lose weight at home is with exercise. Exercises help you burn extra calories and build muscle. You'll feel stronger and more confident after completing a few short workouts. Plus, you'll feel healthier and have more energy as you lose weight. Taken together, these benefits make workouts extremely beneficial for weight loss.</p>
<p><br>Most people find it easy to stick to a <a href="https://getshredgo.net/best-online-personal-trainer-for-weight-loss-india/">workout plan</a> when they go to the gym. They're surrounded by equipment they can use and other people who are also working out. None of that exists at home and people get bored from lack of stimulation easily. There's also little reason to work out once you get all of the necessary equipment at home. That includes cardio machines, weights, a kitchen, and a TV with cable or streaming services. All you need is a spot where you can stretch out on the floor and do your exercises.</p>
<p><img src="https://i.postimg.cc/d09DCd40/jenny-ueberberg-Ba-Se-K7rwc1-A-unsplash-1.jpg"></p>
<p>Exercising at home is a lot more effective than dieting alone. People tend to lose more weight when they work out consistently. This is due to the fact that they're building muscle and burning extra calories each day. Additionally, they're able to workout in private without anyone bothering them. That leaves them free from their concerns about looking or feeling weak. Instead, they focus on becoming stronger and healthier without breaking rules or stressing about their appearance.</p>
<p><br>There are many ways you can workout at home to lose weight effectively. You can follow<a href="https://getshredgo.net/tags/deit-plans/"> nutrition plans</a> for effective calorie burning and muscle building exercises for strength gains. There are even apps that help you track your food intake for diet plans. You can also use walking or jogging machines to increase your cardio output and strengthen your heart health further. All of these work together to give you the best possible results from your workouts.</p>
<p><br>Working out at home is an excellent way to lose weight effectively without busting your balls in the gym. Exercises are easy to follow and extremely effective for weight loss- as long as you have enough space and a plan in mind. It's also much easier to stay focused while getting fit at home compared to the gym. There's no reason not to try losing weight at home!</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Post Pregnancy Weight Loss: Tips, Diet Plan &amp; Foods to Eat</title>
        <author>
            <name>Rish</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://getshredgo.net/post-pregnancy-weight-loss-tips-diet-plan-and-foods-to-eat/"/>
        <id>https://getshredgo.net/post-pregnancy-weight-loss-tips-diet-plan-and-foods-to-eat/</id>
        <media:content url="https://getshredgo.net/media/posts/18/juan-encalada-SCteCA0Mf1A-unsplash.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="Deit Plans"/>

        <updated>2022-10-01T04:36:54+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://getshredgo.net/media/posts/18/juan-encalada-SCteCA0Mf1A-unsplash.jpg" alt="" />
                    Most new mothers struggle to shed off the pounds they gained during pregnancy; however, the struggle is even farther greater&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://getshredgo.net/media/posts/18/juan-encalada-SCteCA0Mf1A-unsplash.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p>Most new mothers struggle to shed off the pounds they gained during pregnancy; however, the struggle is even farther greater when the new mother attempts to lose pregnancy weight after having her baby, particularly if she is struggling to follow the suggestions of her prenatal trainer.</p>
<p>The most significant deviation from your body composition prior to pregnancy is often weight gain. This article will assist you gain weight after pregnancy by shedding light on the important factors, which play a role in this form of weight gain and how to lose weight fast. Detailed information on post-pregnancy weight loss, the average time it will take you to achieve the flat belly you strive for post pregnancy, how to accelerate post pregnancy weight loss and options to follow for fast weight loss as well as ways to avoid fast weight loss will follow.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img  src="https://i.postimg.cc/qRQK53cD/filipp-romanovski-RZjd-I8s9be-U-unsplash.jpg" alt="Post Partum Weight Loss Diet Myths Busted Best Online Personal Trainer" width="702" height="469"></figure>
<p>New mothers in this age frequently feel weighed down with shame about their increase in perceived weight. However, they are not alone in this—post-pregnancy weight gain is very natural and nothing they do needs to be ashamed of. The weight will go away more naturally than they gained it. They simply need to be active, practice good dietary habits, and understand the rhythm in which their body works. Losing weight requires a positive mindset and trust in their efforts.</p>
<p>If you are interested in losing post-pregnancy weight, you need to follow a recommended post pregnancy diet, eat the food types recommended, avoid dangerous food types for you and your unborn child, and maintain healthy levels of activity. You must also have sufficient sleep, eat meals at appropriate times, engage in healthy activities, and drink the recommended cold water amount.</p>
<h3 id="post-pregnancy-weight-gain" class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><strong>Post pregnancy weight gain</strong></h3>
<p>The post pregnancy weight that we gain comes from a variety of factors. Our appetite increases when we are pregnant to be under the regulation of hormones entering our bloodstream; Growth Hormone and human chorionic gonadotropin (HCG). The former regulates our digestion, metabolism, the energy and nutrition distribution, as well as our ability to retrieve energy in order to focus or perform the very important task of breastfeeding. The latter hormone helps regulate our pregnancy. That hunger makes us add to our bodily appearance by gaining weight, since the energy and food derived from the food we eat is directed to labour and energy for the baby. As a result, we gain weight that can stay on ranging up to six months after birth, continuing even while breastfeeding. </p>
<p>Most pregnant women who are now the primary caregivers for their children will experience stress and depression. Cortisol rises in their blood and increases their appetite and forces fat storage in the lower abdominal area. This puts many mothers in a state of “eating their feelings” and encourages further weight gain.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img  src="https://i.postimg.cc/MHTB2pd6/juan-encalada-SCte-CA0-Mf1-A-unsplash.jpg" alt="Post Partum Weight Loss Diet Myths Busted Best Online Personal Trainer" width="702" height="468"></figure>
<h2 id="tips-lose-post-pregnancy-weight" class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><strong>Tips to lose post pregnancy weight</strong></h2>
<p>Discussed below are a handful of tips on how to lose weight after pregnancy naturally</p>
<h3 class="align-center msg msg--highlight "><strong>Examine your diet to understand your cravings</strong></h3>
<p>Yes, pregnancy cravings are real. During the first half of my pregnancy, I longed for juicy cheeseburgers. As a nearly full-time vegetarian until pregnancy, this meat-craving behavior was unusual. While cravings can’t always be explained, we can look to the nutrients our bodies might be needing.For me, maybe I needed more protein, fat, and iron — three nutrients found in red meat. Although cheeseburgers are easy to eat for every lunch and dinner, I knew the long-term effects wouldn’t be the best for me and my baby. I made an effort to prepare high-protein meals, including recipes with chicken, fish, and beans. Most of the greasy restaurant cheeseburgers I wanted were replaced with leaner, hearty alternatives. These wholesome meals helped curb my cravings by keeping me full and satisfied.To ensure you and your baby get what you need, your diet should include several minerals and nutrients — namely calcium, iron, and folate.</p>
<h3 class="align-center msg msg--highlight "><strong>Drink plenty of water</strong></h3>
<p>Keeping yourself hydrated is good for your body for several reasons. First, it increases your metabolism and helps you keep in shape, and It also helps you control your appetite by making you feel full. Also, if you notice whether or not your urine is clear, it means that you are not being hydrated enough.</p>
<h3 class="align-center msg msg--highlight "><strong>Exercise</strong></h3>
<p>You can follow a post pregnancy weight loss diet plan for post pregnancy weight loss. However, in most cases, following a post pregnancy weight loss diet won’t be enough to deliver the weight loss results you want. If you want to enjoy rapid weight loss after pregnancy, you have to include an exercise routine as part of your post pregnancy weight loss plan. Think of incorporating a weight training or aerobic workout to burn those calories and strengthen your muscles and bones. New mothers should try and keep time aside to exercise in their daily routines- not just for post pregnancy weight loss, it has numerous other benefits to offer. It can help them relieve the stress they are experiencing with a new baby in the house, perk up their mood and improve their sleep quality.</p>
<h3 class="align-center msg msg--highlight "><strong>Don’t compromise on sleep</strong></h3>
<p>Now, this might seem like a tricky prospect with a toddler hankering for your attention 24/7, but lack of sleep can really affect your post pregnancy weight loss plans. When you are sleep-deprived, you tend to make unhealthy lifestyle choices like binge eating and drinking, which do nothing to help you lose weight. If you are exhausted throughout the day because you didn’t get ample sleep during the night, your body will release the cortisol hormone, which will aggravate your hunger pangs.</p>
<h3 class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><strong>Have realistic expectations</strong></h3>
<p>Yes, celebrity post pregnancy weight loss stories may have you believe that you can go back to your pre-pregnancy body in a couple of months, but these stories are often not 100% true.<br>Even if they are – don’t forget they have an entire team working for them, charting out their post pregnancy weight loss journey. Research has found that the average time to lose baby weight can exceed a year. It could take a year or two for you to return to your pre-pregnancy body, if at all.</p>
<h3 class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><strong>Keep healthy snacks close at hand</strong></h3>
<p>Breastfeeding mothers are subject to sudden hunger and spikes in their appetite. If not handled well, these hunger spikes could lead to weight gain. Instead, if you stock up on fruits, sprouts, vegetables, nuts and yoghurt to feed on, when hungry – you could help bring down the average time to lose the baby weight, in your case.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img  src="https://i.postimg.cc/x84z0V4K/jonathan-borba-bpo-Ly-Sr6-P-E-unsplash.jpg" alt="Post Partum Weight Loss Diet Myths Busted Best Online Personal Trainer" width="702" height="468"></figure>
<h3 id="post-pregnancy-diet-plan" class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><strong>Post-pregnancy diet plan</strong></h3>
<p>Your post pregnancy weight loss diet should never be a crash diet. You should be looking to lose your pregnancy weight gradually and effectively with a reliable post pregnancy weight loss diet plan.</p>
<p class="msg msg--success">Women need between 1500-2200 calories daily to maintain regular bodily function. If you are breastfeeding, you should consume a minimum of 1800 calories, for the proper nourishment of both you and your body.</p>
<p>Aim to lose approximately 1.5 pounds on a weekly basis; you don’t want extremely rapid weight loss after pregnancy. If you lose weight too rapidly after your pregnancy, your body can release toxins into your blood contaminating your breast milk, which could prove severely harmful for the nursing child. If you’ve been consuming calories above the bare minimum, try to cut down 500 calories daily from your diet. You could do this by either eating smaller portions or increasing your activity levels.</p>
<p>Most post pregnancy weight loss diet plans advice new mothers to eat 5-6 small meals in a day interspersed with healthy snacks. They also ask women to try to avoid skipping meals, as this does more harm than good, and they end up eating in excess at other meals. Never miss breakfast, especially when you’re following a post pregnancy weight loss diet plan. It will keep you from feeling an energy lag later in the day and help you get your daily tasks done in a more focused manner.</p>
<h2 id="foods-to-eat">Foods to eat</h2>
<p>After you’ve made up your mind to get started on your post pregnancy weight loss diet plan, make sure that you are eating the right food products in alignment with your goal. The following food products will help you:</p>
<h3 class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><strong>Fiber</strong></h3>
<p>Food rich in fiber improves your digestive health. Consuming soluble fiber keeps your hunger hormones in check and helps you eat less as a result.</p>
<h3 class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><strong>Protein</strong></h3>
<p>Lean meat, eggs, fish, dairy and other sources of healthy protein can boost your metabolism and bring down your calorie intake by decreasing your appetite.</p>
<h3 class="align-center msg msg--highlight "><strong>Complex Carbohydrates</strong></h3>
<p>Complex carbohydrates provide you with energy all around the day, as they take longer to break down.</p>
<h3 class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><strong>Unsaturated and Polyunsaturated fats</strong></h3>
<p>Don’t stop consuming fat completely in a bid to lose weight post-pregnancy. Instead, eat food rich in unsaturated and polyunsaturated fats which keep your body healthy and improve cardiac function.</p>
<h2 id="foods-to-avoid">Foods to avoid</h2>
<p>There are certain food items you must avoid if you want to succeed in your post pregnancy weight loss. These are:</p>
<h3 class="align-center msg msg--highlight "><strong>Food with added sugar and/or refined carbohydrates</strong></h3>
<p>Food rich in sugar and refined carbs have low nutrient value and yet, are high in calories. Consuming food with high calorific value and low nutrient value can increase your weight, up your risk of developing heart health issues, cancer and diabetes. Try to steer clear of fizzy and sugary drinks and other such processed food variants such as packaged biscuits, cakes and the like. Opt for whole foods instead. If you must consume something sweet, go for desserts from an organic bakery as opposed to processed and packaged cookies.</p>
<h3 class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><strong>Processed food products</strong></h3>
<p>As already discussed, processed food is unhealthy for you. Fast food and pre-packed food are examples of processed food, high in sugar, unhealthy fat, calories and salt. All of these are detrimental to your weight loss efforts. Try to consume nutrient-dense, fresh whole foods like fruits and vegetables instead.</p>
<h3 class="msg msg--highlight  align-center"><strong>Alcohol</strong></h3>
<p>Alcohol is calorie-dense, but it provides no nutrition. Alcohol consumption also leads to belly fat. Not only does it counteract your postpartum weight loss attempts, but it can also be unhealthy for your baby. Minimal amounts of alcohol can be passed over to your child via your breast milk. Alcohol consumption can also temporarily reduce your breast milk volume. Not to mention, the dependency you might develop which would interfere with your regular sleep quality.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img  src="https://i.postimg.cc/597v5826/jonathan-borba-8-C-Iaq-Aujw-M-unsplash.jpg" alt="Post Partum Weight Loss Diet Myths Busted Best Online Personal Trainer" width="702" height="468"></figure>
<h1>Pregnancy health myths debunked</h1>
<h3>Myth 1: You can’t eat seafood</h3>
<p class="Body">The mercury levels in fish make them a talking point for pregnancies. Most fish, <a href="https://www.fda.gov/Food/ResourcesForYou/Consumers/ucm393070.htm" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="content-link css-5r4717">according to the FDA<span class="css-1mdvjzu icon-hl-trusted-source-after"><span class="sro">Trusted Source</span></span></a>, are safe if they’re not consumed in abundance. Some of the safe choices include:</p>
<ul>
<li>canned tuna</li>
<li>salmon</li>
<li>catfish</li>
<li>crab</li>
</ul>
<p class="Body">The FDA has a full list <a href="https://www.fda.gov/Food/ResourcesForYou/Consumers/ucm393070.htm" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="content-link css-5r4717">here<span class="css-1mdvjzu icon-hl-trusted-source-after"><span class="sro">Trusted Source</span></span></a>.</p>
<p class="Body">There’s a lot of benefits to seafood, like healthy fats which aid in a baby’s development. Just cap your seafood intake to <a href="https://academic.oup.com/aje/article/183/3/169/2195469" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="content-link css-5r4717">340 grams a week</a>, and avoid raw sushi to limit your risk of exposure to certain bacteria.</p>
<h3>Myth 2: You should avoid exercise and exertion</h3>
<p class="Body">If you’re healthy and have the go-ahead from your physician, it’s safe to continue doing most types of exercise, says the <a href="https://www.acog.org/Patients/FAQs/Exercise-During-Pregnancy" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="content-link css-5r4717">American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists</a>.</p>
<p class="Body">Some risks are associated with certain exercises — like horseback riding and contact sports — but that doesn’t mean you should avoid physical activity altogether. <a href="https://getshredgo.net/tags/diet-and-exercise/">Regular exercise</a> is extremely beneficial for both mom and baby, and can even alleviate pain points of pregnancy.</p>
<h3>Myth 3: You’re not allowed to enjoy hot baths</h3>
<p class="Body">Based on an old tale that people who are pregnant should avoid heat stress, many still believe they can’t soak in a hot bath.</p>
<p>New recommendations, however, state that hot baths and exercise are safe during pregnancy, as long as your body temperature doesn’t go above 102.2°F.</p>
<h3>Myth 4: You can’t drink coffee</h3>
<p class="Body">While it was previously believed that caffeine could cause a miscarriage, <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3625078/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" class="content-link css-5r4717">research shows<span class="css-1mdvjzu icon-hl-trusted-source-after"><span class="sro">Trusted Source</span></span></a> that one to two cups per day is entirely safe. So no need to ditch your morning latte as your go-to energy boost!</p>
<h3 id="summary" class="align-center msg msg--highlight "><strong>Summary</strong></h3>
<p>Hopefully, our article helped you in understanding how to lose weight after pregnancy naturally. To conclude, we will try to comprehend the average time to lose the baby weight by a new mother. <em><strong>It is generally recommended that mothers don’t weigh themselves at least until two weeks after pregnancy</strong></em>. Even then, measuring waist size is probably a better idea as their weight won’t be reflective of their body fat only.</p>
<p>Mothers on a post-pregnancy weight loss diet plan may begin to show results of their weight loss efforts from the first month after conceiving itself. Women are medically advised to gain 25-30 pounds during their pregnancy to be able to amply nourish their baby. Some mothers can lose up to 20 pounds in the first month itself, meaning, they may already be back to their pre-baby body.</p>
<p class="msg msg--success">Six weeks from your date of conception, you will notice that your belly now looks flatter and smaller. If you have been successful in sticking to your postpartum weight loss endeavours, you will most likely have returned to your original weight before pregnancy, a couple of months post it.</p>
<p>Generally, nine months is the average time to lose baby weight, unless you had gained extra weight during your pregnancy. However, this is no blanket rule. Every woman loses their post-pregnancy weight on their own time, depending on the diet they are eating and the amount of exercise they are getting daily.</p>
<p>Don’t give in to fad diets hoping for rapid weight loss after pregnancy. It will harm you and your baby. Eat a healthy diet rich in proteins, complex carbs and fiber, drink enough water and get some much-needed rest and the occasional exercise, besides running after your child and you should be good. You will have lost all the excess weight giving you grief in no time at all.</p>
<h2 id="faqs">Frequently Asked Questions</h2>
<p> </p>
<div class="schema-faq wp-block-yoast-faq-block">
<div class="schema-faq-section"><strong class="schema-faq-question">Q. How long does it usually take to lose weight after having a baby?</strong></div>
<div class="schema-faq-section"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">A: It depends on the weight gain. Woman can aim to lose 2 kg per month post pregnancy.</span></div>
<div> </div>
<div class="schema-faq-section"><strong class="schema-faq-question">Q. Is it harder to lose weight after second baby?</strong><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">A: No, not at all. If you maintain your lifestyle balance which includes your diet, physical activity, sleep and water intake, you can easily lose weight and stay healthy.</span></div>
<div> </div>
<div class="schema-faq-section"><strong class="schema-faq-question">Q. How do you lose belly fat while breastfeeding?</strong></div>
<div class="schema-faq-section"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">A: Breast feeding itself is an extensive activity which burns many calories, especially if you feed in sitting position. Along with this, if you eat a well balanced diet rich in protein and fiber, eat small and frequent meals, take minimum 10-12 glasses of water, maintain some regular physical activity like walking, etc. then you can easily lose belly fat.</span></div>
<div> </div>
<div class="schema-faq-section"><strong class="schema-faq-question">Q. Why have I gained weight after pregnancy?</strong></div>
<div class="schema-faq-section"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">A: There are several reasons why women gain weight post pregnancy</span></div>
<ul>
<li class="schema-faq-section"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">Erratic and irregular eating pattern, and long gaps between each meal.</span></li>
<li class="schema-faq-section"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">It’s important to eat calorie rich food to meet lactation needs, but it is required to get calories from protein, fiber, complex carbohydrates and good fat sources. Most people tend to focus on eating simple carbs and fats like panjeeris, oily fried foods, sweets, desserts, cereals , refined products etc.</span></li>
<li class="schema-faq-section"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">Less intake of water</span></li>
<li class="schema-faq-section"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">Poor sleeping pattern</span></li>
<li class="schema-faq-section"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">Lack of activity</span></li>
</ul>
</div>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Weight Gain Calculator</title>
        <author>
            <name>Rish</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://getshredgo.net/weight-gain-calculator/"/>
        <id>https://getshredgo.net/weight-gain-calculator/</id>
            <category term="Tools"/>

        <updated>2022-10-28T15:42:54+05:30</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <div class="omni-calculator" data-calculator="health/weight-gain" data-width="auto" data-config="{&quot;height&quot;:{&quot;unitDefault&quot;:&quot;ftinch&quot;},&quot;sex&quot;:{&quot;default&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}}" data-currency="INR" data-show-row-controls="false" data-version="3" data-t="1664563601416">
<div class="omni-calculator-header"> </div>
<div class="omni-calculator-footer"><a href="https://www.omnicalculator.com/health/weight-gain" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><figure class="omni-calculator-logo"><img  src="https://cdn.omnicalculator.com/embed/omni-calculator-logo-long.svg" alt="Omni"></figure></a></div>
</div>
<p>
<script async="" src="https://cdn.omnicalculator.com/sdk.js"></script>
</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>TDEE Calculator</title>
        <author>
            <name>Rish</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://getshredgo.net/tdee-calculator/"/>
        <id>https://getshredgo.net/tdee-calculator/</id>
            <category term="Tools"/>

        <updated>2022-10-28T15:42:59+05:30</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <div class="omni-calculator" data-calculator="health/tdee" data-width="auto" data-config="{}" data-currency="INR" data-show-row-controls="false" data-version="3" data-t="1664563349283">
<div class="omni-calculator-header"> </div>
<div class="omni-calculator-footer"><a href="https://www.omnicalculator.com/health/tdee" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><figure class="omni-calculator-logo"><img  src="https://cdn.omnicalculator.com/embed/omni-calculator-logo-long.svg" alt="Omni"></figure></a></div>
</div>
<p>
<script async="" src="https://cdn.omnicalculator.com/sdk.js"></script>
</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Ideal Weight Calculator</title>
        <author>
            <name>Rish</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://getshredgo.net/ideal-weight-calculator/"/>
        <id>https://getshredgo.net/ideal-weight-calculator/</id>
            <category term="Tools"/>

        <updated>2022-10-28T15:44:45+05:30</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <div class="omni-calculator" data-calculator="health/ideal-weight" data-width="auto" data-config="{&quot;height&quot;:{&quot;unitDefault&quot;:&quot;ftinch&quot;},&quot;sex&quot;:{&quot;default&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}}" data-currency="INR" data-show-row-controls="false" data-version="3" data-t="1664563227719">
<div class="omni-calculator-header"> </div>
<div class="omni-calculator-footer"><a href="https://www.omnicalculator.com/health/ideal-weight" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><figure class="omni-calculator-logo"><img  src="https://cdn.omnicalculator.com/embed/omni-calculator-logo-long.svg" alt="Omni"></figure></a></div>
</div>
<p>
<script async="" src="https://cdn.omnicalculator.com/sdk.js"></script>
</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Body Fat Calculator</title>
        <author>
            <name>Rish</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://getshredgo.net/body-fat-calculator/"/>
        <id>https://getshredgo.net/body-fat-calculator/</id>
            <category term="Tools"/>

        <updated>2022-10-28T15:43:09+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Body Fat Calculator
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <div class="omni-calculator" data-calculator="health/navy-body-fat" data-width="auto" data-config="{&quot;Height&quot;:{&quot;unitDefault&quot;:&quot;ftinch&quot;},&quot;sex&quot;:{&quot;default&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}}" data-currency="INR" data-show-row-controls="false" data-version="3" data-t="1664563063186">
<div class="omni-calculator-header">Body Fat Calculator</div>
<div class="omni-calculator-footer"><a href="https://www.omnicalculator.com/health/navy-body-fat" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><figure class="omni-calculator-logo"><img  src="https://cdn.omnicalculator.com/embed/omni-calculator-logo-long.svg" alt="Omni"></figure></a></div>
</div>
<p>
<script async="" src="https://cdn.omnicalculator.com/sdk.js"></script>
</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>BMI Calculator</title>
        <author>
            <name>Rish</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://getshredgo.net/bmi-calculator/"/>
        <id>https://getshredgo.net/bmi-calculator/</id>
            <category term="Tools"/>

        <updated>2022-10-28T15:43:15+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    BMI Calculator
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <div class="omni-calculator" data-calculator="health/bmi" data-width="auto" data-config="{&quot;height&quot;:{&quot;unitDefault&quot;:&quot;ftinch&quot;},&quot;athlete&quot;:{&quot;advanced&quot;:true},&quot;sex&quot;:{&quot;advanced&quot;:false,&quot;default&quot;:&quot;2&quot;},&quot;age&quot;:{&quot;advanced&quot;:true}}" data-currency="INR" data-show-row-controls="false" data-version="3" data-t="1664562675967">
<div class="omni-calculator-header">BMI Calculator</div>
<div class="omni-calculator-footer"><a href="https://www.omnicalculator.com/health/bmi" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><figure class="omni-calculator-logo"><img  src="https://cdn.omnicalculator.com/embed/omni-calculator-logo-long.svg" alt="Omni"></figure></a></div>
</div>
<p>
<script async="" src="https://cdn.omnicalculator.com/sdk.js"></script>
</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>PCOD vs PCOS and how to manage both</title>
        <author>
            <name>Rish</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://getshredgo.net/pcod-vs-pcos-and-how-to-manage-both/"/>
        <id>https://getshredgo.net/pcod-vs-pcos-and-how-to-manage-both/</id>
        <media:content url="https://getshredgo.net/media/posts/12/engin-akyurt-qU5FbP_i8-I-unsplash.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="Disease Prevention"/>

        <updated>2022-09-30T04:59:01+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://getshredgo.net/media/posts/12/engin-akyurt-qU5FbP_i8-I-unsplash.jpg" alt="" />
                    Women of reproductive age from the adolescent stage onwards start with hormonal fluctuations. These fluctuations might lead to various endocrine&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://getshredgo.net/media/posts/12/engin-akyurt-qU5FbP_i8-I-unsplash.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p>Women of reproductive age from the adolescent stage onwards start with hormonal fluctuations. These fluctuations might lead to various endocrine and metabolic disorders. PCOD or PCOS commonly known are metabolic disorders concerned with the ovaries.</p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight ">The ovary is a reproductive organ that changes its form, appearance, and shape according to its hormonal environment. But are PCOD and PCOS both the same? Let’s learn the differences between these two endocrine disorders.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img  src="https://i.postimg.cc/Pr6J4SKW/engin-akyurt-q-U5-Fb-P-i8-I-unsplash.jpg" alt="How to manage PCOS and PCOD with diet" width="702" height="468"></figure>
<h2><strong>What is PCOD?</strong></h2>
<p><strong>PCOD </strong>called Polycystic Ovarian Disease is a condition where the ovaries contain multiple immature eggs which later get converted into fluid-filled spaces called cysts. This condition is mainly hereditary and is passed from mothers through generations. The main underlying cause for this condition is a hormonal imbalance, especially an increase in the androgens (male hormones). It is a highly common condition and more prevalent in women of the age group 12-45 years.</p>
<p><strong>The clinical features of PCOD are:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li aria-level="1">Irregular ovulation.</li>
<li aria-level="1">Obesity.</li>
<li aria-level="1">Alopecia or Male pattern baldness.</li>
<li aria-level="1">Irregular periods.</li>
<li aria-level="1">Difficulty in conception.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>PCOS</strong> called Polycystic Ovarian Syndrome is a condition more severe than PCOD. <span class="gvxzyvdx aeinzg81 t7p7dqev gh25dzvf tb6i94ri gupuyl1y i2onq4tn b6ax4al1 gem102v4 ncib64c9 mrvwc6qr sx8pxkcf f597kf1v cpcgwwas m2nijcs8 hxfwr5lz k1z55t6l oog5qr5w tes86rjd pbevjfx6 ztn2w49o" dir="auto">The polycystic ovary syndrome is one of the most common cause of infertility due to anovulation which affects 4-7% of women following criteria are sufficient for the diagnosis.oligo and/0r anovulation,clinical and/or biochemical signs of hyperandrogenism and polycystic ovaries at ultrasound. </span>In this, the ovaries produce more male hormones, which leads to a higher number of non-functional follicles/cysts in the ovaries per cycle. The higher number of these cysts leads to anovulatory cycles, where a mature egg is not available for fertilization. This leads to infertility. </p>
<figure class="post__image"><img  src="https://i.postimg.cc/BnX6w2wd/linkedin-sales-solutions-VKJt1-EZHl-Ws-unsplash.jpg" alt="How to manage PCOS and PCOD with diet" width="702" height="468"></figure>
<p><strong>The clinical features of PCOS are:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li aria-level="1">Enlarged and bulky ovaries with more than 10ml volume, leading to overproduction of androgens.</li>
<li aria-level="1">More than 12  follicles, each measuring 2 to 9 millimeters in diameter, organized around the lining of the ovary like a necklace.</li>
<li aria-level="1">Irregular or missing periods.</li>
<li aria-level="1">Heavy periods.</li>
<li aria-level="1">Acne.</li>
<li aria-level="1">Hair loss (male pattern baldness).</li>
<li aria-level="1">Android (Apple-shaped) type of obesity. </li>
<li aria-level="1">Infertility.</li>
<li aria-level="1">Insulin resistance.</li>
<li aria-level="1">Gestational diabetes.</li>
<li aria-level="1">Excess body-weight.</li>
<li aria-level="1">Hirsutism (excess hair growth on various parts of the body).</li>
</ul>
<p class="msg msg--highlight ">PCOS, if left untreated, leads to other lifestyle disorders like obesity, type 2 diabetes and increase in blood cholesterol levels.</p>
<p>The physical changes seen in PCOS can severely affect the confidence or self-esteem of women and their body image that contributes to psychological disturbances like anxiety and depression. Another factor that also affects their mental health is the societal pressure to have children as they struggle hard to conceive.</p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight "><strong><span class="gvxzyvdx aeinzg81 t7p7dqev gh25dzvf tb6i94ri gupuyl1y i2onq4tn b6ax4al1 gem102v4 ncib64c9 mrvwc6qr sx8pxkcf f597kf1v cpcgwwas m2nijcs8 hxfwr5lz k1z55t6l oog5qr5w tes86rjd pbevjfx6 ztn2w49o" dir="auto">PCOS has no cure.</span></strong></p>
<p><span class="gvxzyvdx aeinzg81 t7p7dqev gh25dzvf tb6i94ri gupuyl1y i2onq4tn b6ax4al1 gem102v4 ncib64c9 mrvwc6qr sx8pxkcf f597kf1v cpcgwwas m2nijcs8 hxfwr5lz k1z55t6l oog5qr5w tes86rjd pbevjfx6 ztn2w49o" dir="auto">However, it is proven to be manageable by doing lifestyle changes such as weight loss, following a low carb diet and exercise.</span></p>
<figure class="post__image"><img  src="https://i.postimg.cc/YCZ9cj5j/naomi-august-a-Lnq-Dp3-B3-YU-unsplash.jpg" alt="How to manage PCOS and PCOD with diet" width="702" height="468"></figure>
<h2><strong>Understanding the difference between PCOD and PCOS</strong></h2>
<p>The exact reasons for these disorders are not known, but a few theories suggest a myriad of abnormalities. The abnormalities could be, low levels of hormones like progesterone due to infrequent ovulation, overproduction of androgens which could trigger insulin resistance and abnormal androgen levels that signals the over-production of follicles.</p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight ">PCOS is a metabolic syndrome, whereas PCOD is a milder condition that can improve with the right nutrition &amp; exercise.</p>
<p>Women with PCOS are at a higher risk for other comorbidities like insulin resistance, diabetes, cardiovascular disorders &amp; endometrial cancers.</p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight ">Symptoms of PCOS like excess facial hair, acne, weight gain are visible at an early age.</p>
<p>Women with PCOD do not have many issues getting pregnant as seeking medical advice can help drastically, but those with PCOS have a higher risk of infertility &amp; also risk of miscarriage.</p>
<p>Women with PCOD may ovulate despite having symptoms similar to that of PCOS. But in the latter condition, ovulation is hampered due to the severe hormonal imbalance.</p>
<p>Ovaries in PCOS are very bulky with high volume &amp; contain approximately 12-15 cysts. Ovaries with PCOD in contrast may not be very bulky and may contain around 5-8 cysts.</p>
<p>Lastly, PCOS is not as common as PCOD.</p>
<figure class="post__image"><img  src="https://i.postimg.cc/zfhfq8N7/thought-catalog-UK78i6v-K3sc-unsplash.jpg" alt="How to manage PCOS and PCOD with diet" width="702" height="468"></figure>
<p class="msg msg--highlight "><strong>How to manage PCOS / PCOD Condition</strong></p>
<ul>
<li aria-level="1">Weight loss with an increase in fat-free mass is the mainstay for improvement of both PCOD &amp; PCOS according to the International Evidence-based Guideline for the Assessment and Management of PCOS.</li>
<li aria-level="1">As insulin resistance is mostly associated with PCOS, women should cut down on simple sugars &amp; rather include more whole foods rich in complex carbohydrates in their diet.</li>
<li aria-level="1">Weight loss will not just increase the chances of ovulation &amp; subsequent pregnancy, but also minimize the risk of miscarriage.</li>
<li aria-level="1">Regular physical activity &amp; a balanced diet can help in long-term weight management.</li>
<li aria-level="1">An appropriate and effective dietary recommendation is still a debate for PCOS. According to a few studies, dietary intake was assessed in women with PCOS, and it was found that these women consumed high glycemic index carbohydrates such as white bread and fried potatoes. Of all the popular diets, the Mediterranean diet promotes low GI carbohydrates, high fiber, unsaturated fats, vegetables and fruits (a rich source of vitamins and antioxidants) and is found to be effective in the management of various lifestyle disorders like insulin resistance, diabetes, hypercholesterolemia etc. Hence, it is also suggested for women with PCOS though this requires more supportive evidence. .</li>
<li aria-level="1">Lean women with PCOS should aim to maintain the bodyweight with consumption of a balanced diet as mentioned in the dietary recommendations. This can help with improving insulin resistance and overproduction of androgens.</li>
<li aria-level="1">Increasing the level of physical activity (either aerobic or anaerobic) aimed at reducing BMI, helps reduce the ovarian volume &amp; also the number of follicles.</li>
<li aria-level="1">A recent study has shown that high intensity aerobic activity of at least 3 days per week for 30 min or more per day with greater than or equal to 60% of VO2 max is advised to improve insulin resistance. Also, a combination workout that includes strength or resistance training thrice a week may help with managing the androgen levels.</li>
<li aria-level="1">Excess hair growth (hirsutism) due to PCOS/PCOD can be managed by various methods like laser hair removal treatment and the use of oral contraceptives to suppress androgen production.</li>
<li aria-level="1">Acne that is mild to moderate can be treated with topical applications like benzoyl peroxide or clindamycin creams.</li>
<li aria-level="1">For mental health in women with PCOS, physical exercise, in turn, group exercise has shown a  better outcome of quality of life.</li>
</ul>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
